<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE issue SYSTEM "lwg-issue.dtd" [ 
  <!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
] >

<issue num="23" status="WP">
<title>Output iterators without value types</title>
<section><sref ref="[output.iterators]"/></section>
<submitter>LWG</submitter>
<date>28 Feb 2008</date>

<discussion>
  <p>24.1.2 preserves the C++03 notion that output iterators don't
  actually have value types (see, for example, 24.1.2 paragraph 3,
  saying that an output iterator may permit output of many different
  value types). Is this something we really want to preserve for
  conceptized C++09? There are a few real-world output iterators that
  support multiple output types, but very few. For most users, the
  fact that we don't have a specific output types is much more a
  nuisance than anything else. This is another issue where we have a
  choice between rationalizing the current requirements or preserving
  them in every last corner case, and we should consider doing the
  former. Concretely, in terms of the n2500 notation: most users
  probably want to use the <tt>BasicOutputIterator</tt> concept,
  not <tt>OutputIterator</tt>. We should consider
  renaming <tt>BasicOutputIterator</tt> to <tt>OutputIterator</tt>,
  and either getting rid of the concept that n2500
  calls <tt>OutputIterator</tt> or renaming it
  to <tt>BackwardCompatibilityOutputIteratorWithoutValueType</tt>.</p>

  <p><b>Doug Gregor</b>: Note that the output iterator without a value
  type (currently called <code>OutputIterator</code>) is used by many
  of the algorithms in chapter 25. In fact, none of these algorithms
  use <code>BasicOutputIterator</code> (the one that has a value
  type). It would be a shame for all of our algorithms to have a name
  like <code>BackwardCompatibilityOutputIteratorWithoutValueType</code>
  in their requires clauses. Changing these algorithms to use the
  output iterator with a value type (currently
  called <code>BasicOutputIterator</code>) would break backward
  compatibility significantly, and is therefore probably not
  feasible.</p>
</discussion>

<resolution>
  <p><code>BasicOutputIterator</code> has been removed with the latest
  refactoring of the iterator taxonomy.</p>
</resolution>

</issue>
